I have a show every day on the sputnik
connect work with Brian Becker
it's called loud and clear and to tell
you the truth I'm very proud of it I
want to preface this by saying that when
I was first interviewed for this this
job spudnick approached me they offered
it to me and I said well I don't know
it's you know it's it's owned by the
Russian government I said I if I took
this job I would want complete freedom
to talk about any issue I wanted and to
be able to criticize anybody I wanted
including Vladimir Putin and they said
done and I said really are you willing
to put it in writing they said yes done
and they did I've been there for almost
a year and a half now no one has ever
asked me to say something or to not say
something no one has ever asked me to
take a certain position I have utter and
complete freedom to say anything that I
want so with that in mind Ryan and I
decided to do a weekly segment for 30
minutes every Thursday
it runs from 4:30 to 5:00 o'clock
Eastern Time every day called criminal
and justice in which we look at the
criminal justice system across the
country we look at things like
sentencing reform criminal justice
reform and frankly we look a lot at
crooked cops and crooked prosecutors and
crooked judges and these things are just
a part of everyday life is these are a
fact of the American justice system well
when you know last week the Washington
Post publishes an article quite a long
article in which it quotes a new study
written by - two eggheads from the
Center for Strategic and International
Studies
CSIS one of these people is a former
Assistant Secretary of Homeland Security
in the Obama administration and they
point out our show in particular by name
they mentioned the segment criminal
justice injustice by name and their
conclusion is that because we are on a
Russian state
nation and we are criticizing the
American judicial system that we are
weakening democracy democracy itself
we're damaging the American democratic
system my initial reaction was to laughs
I mean it's laughable
it's ridiculous but you know you can't
laugh because people are serious about
this kind of thing this is how upside
down we've become in Washington
it's another Red Scare all over again
and I have friends who consider
themselves to be lifelong progressives
who will look at you straight in the eye
and say that Russia is the greatest
threat to the United States and to the
American Way of life today and I don't
know whether to laugh or to cry because
if they had any idea that they were
being propagandized it would be
disgusted with themselves but this is a
this is what we're up against a Joe you
live it every day just like I do
Ray McGovern lives it every day I see
Ray's joined us as well and so you know
I just I wish that we could get the word
out to everybody I wish that we could
explain to people and educate people as
to how preposterous this is and how
damaging it is to our way of life if
anything is a threat to our democracy
it's this neo-fascism that we're getting
from what is ostensibly the left and
it's extraordinarily disappointing to me
I also want to I want to echo something
that you said Joe this bone7 situation
is is bad and it's bad because Joshua
Schulte the CIA officer who's been
arrested now remember that for a
whistleblower to be a whistleblower the
criteria are very clear you'd have to
have brought to light any evidence of
waste fraud abuse illegality or threats
to the public health or public safety
motivation is irrelevant we don't know
what his motivation was I don't care
what his motivation was if he brought to
light evidence of waste fraud abuse or
illegality the guy's a whistleblower so
what was he arrested for he was arrested
for possession of child pornography
not on espionage charges not in the
beginning possession of child
pornography now did he have child
pornography I have no idea
the feds said that Matt to heart had
child pornography on his computer when
he was arrested after blowing the
whistle in the military and in fact
there was no such thing on his computer
the judge asked to see the evidence of
child porn there was zero literally zero
evidence of child porn the judge threw
that count out and told the government
not to ever do something like that again
but the reason I'm bringing this up is
that this is a this is a pattern what
drives the government crazy in
whistleblowing cases Joe is when the
public pays attention and support for
the whistleblower begins to grow and so
how do you separate the whistleblower
from his natural constituency from those
who would automatically support him you
charge him with a child sex crime what
could possibly be worse than a child sex
crime but we know now that they make it
up so they charged Matt I'm sorry Josh
Schulte with a sex crime now they've
added multiple counts of espionage
you're right that the new rules and we
know this because he wrote a letter to
to his judge the new rules dictate that
he be taken
manacled shackled leg chains a chain
around the midsection handcuffs and then
the handcuffs are changed to the chains
all right this is how they do it he's
taken in Chains and manacles to the to
the skiff now the skiff is in the
Justice Department's building in New
York he's only allowed to go there from
9:00 to 5:00 now the Justice Department
prosecutors can work 24 hours a day and
believe me they do he can only be there
with his lawyer from 9:00 to 5:00 not
only is he strip searched on the way in
and on the way out
but he has to be changed to an eyebolt
in the floor so he can't move
his lawyer has to be searched going in
and going out that's unprecedented and
then on top of that they have CCTV
cameras inside the vault to watch him at
all times
now the purportedly there is no
listening device but we don't know
there's also an FBI agent that has to be
in the vault with him at all times
but the FBI agent is on his honor not to
report back to the prosecutors what he
and his attorney are talking about now
this isn't justice I'm going to tell you
something that my attorney told me I had
judge Leonie brinkema in my case judge
brinkema is the same judge that Trillian
would have if he were to be returned to
the United States and I pray to God he's
not but with judge brinkema the fixes in
she was a longtime federal prosecutor
before coming to the bench she was a
reagan appointee and then she was
elevated in the clinton administration
but only at the request of john warner
it was a republican conservative
republican senator so she has just she
has prosecution in her soul there's
nothing friendly about her especially in
a national security case well judge
brinkema in my case scheduled a hearing
for us we made 70 separate motions at
one point to declassify 70 documents
that were necessary for my defense and
we blocked off three days in order to
argue these 70 motions we walked into
the courtroom and she said I'm gonna
make everybody's job very easy I'm going
to deny all 70 of these motions she said
to me I don't think you need a single
one of these documents to defend
yourself
well these documents were the only
defense that I had so instead of three
days we were out of court in five
minutes and as we were leaving the
courtroom I said to my lawyer my lead
attorney what just happened in there and
he certainly he turned to me and he said
we just lost the case that's what
happened and I said so what do we do now
and he said now we negotiate a plea I
said I'm not gonna go
because I didn't do anything wrong I'm
gonna go to trial and he stopped me and
he said you know what your problem is
your problem is that you think this is
about justice
this isn't about justice this is about
mitigating damaged and he was exactly
right and that wasn't true just of me
that's true of all of us whether it's
whether it's Reema govern getting
arrested for exercising his
constitutional right to freedom of
speech or Julian Assange brought blowing
the whistle on on war crimes and crimes
against humanity or Josh Schulte posting
classified purportedly classified
documents in the public interest
it's not about justice there is no
justice not in this system it's about
mitigating damage and in a system like
that we can't win
were you ever shackled in that way you
describe it as if you had been oh yes I
was multiple times I broke my finger in
prison at one point and um and they
wouldn't treat it and so my arm was
swollen all the way up to my my elbows
swollen like I couldn't bend my fingers
I couldn't move my hand and then finally
after 16 days they decided to take me
out for an x-ray and and so they
shackled me like that and and worse than
that it's not just the shackling it's
they strip you naked they do a body
cavity search and then they put you in a
uniform made out of paper so it's it's
barely on you right and then over the
paper uniform that's when they put all
the chains and the shackles and the
manacles around your ankles and they
take you out like that it was the dead
of winter right this was the first week
of February that they took me out like
this
it's snow and ice everywhere I don't
have a coat because I'm not allowed to
have a coat because I could I guess hide
something in the coat I supposed so I'm
in this paper uniform naked underneath
shackled they take me to the doctor the
doctor does an x-ray he said you know
your fingers broken your hand is broken
normally I would set it
but you broke it so long ago it's
already begun to heal itself
so he said sorry buddy and I still can't
I still can't bend my finger it won't it
won't Bend but I mean that's that was
minor compared to what some of these
other guys are going through but this is
what Josh Schulte has to go through
every time he wants to see his attorneys
every single time and he's not been
convicted of anything yet yeah and
that's why I like treating him
what could Julian Assange Allah proto if
he should ever get into the hands of
these people literally nothing good I
can tell you what my first day was like
I turned myself in to the FBI on a
Monday morning the FBI actually tried to
arrest me on a Thursday and they do that
on purpose they try to make their
arrests on Thursdays because federal
courts don't arraign anybody on Fridays
and so if you're arrested on Thursday
you have to spend Thursday night Friday
night Saturday night and Sunday night in
the DC jail where you're gonna get
softened up a little bit by a couple of
the guys in there because you're wearing
a suit you're a white middle-class guy
middle-aged guy and so you're gonna have
a tough four days that's exactly what
they want they want you to be beaten
they want you to be humiliated so that
you're more likely to take a quick plea
deal just to get out of that situation
so the only thing that saved me is on
that Thursday afternoon I said I want to
see my attorneys and I want to see them
right now
that was the only thing that saved me
because they had to let me see my
attorneys so I turned myself in on
Monday they handcuffed me in the lobby
of the FBI Washington field office they
walked me 30 feet and then uncuffed me
I took mug shots and fingerprints and
then me they chained me to a bench to a
metal bench i sat there for three hours
and it was I was changes with cuffs so I
had to sit like this cuff to the foot of
the bench I couldn't sit up straight for
three hours like this then they put me
in a Anna's an SUV cuffed behind my back
so that I couldn't sit back I had to sit
leaning forward while they're peeling
through the streets of Washington and
and I'm being tossed all over the back
of the SUV which I learned later they
also do on purpose and then they took me
into the basement of the Federal
Building in our in Alexandria Virginia
this is where Julian would be charged
and then they turn you over to the
marshals so I have never worked with the
marshals before I I don't know any
marshals I had never had any
professional interaction with the March
with the marshals so I walked him I
walked in and I'm in a suit tie
everything cuffed behind my back and
this marshal who could not possibly have
been more than 20 years old shouts up
against the wall [__] and he
pushes me throws me up against the wall
so I I hit I slammed into the wall and I
said oh so this is how it's gonna be huh
tough guy and that just made him angrier
or Foe angrier whatever it was and I
decided you know if he's gonna be a dick
to me I'm gonna be a dick to him so I
kept calling him kid
which just enraged him and then my
punishment was they chained me to the
bench again in the holding cell there
were four of us in this holding cell I
was the only one who was chained and of
the other three guys two were child
molesters who had been caught at the Iwo
Jima you know laying in the bushes for
children and and one was a Chinese drug
smuggler so I was the only one chained
at one point I said listen I'm diabetic
I've been in here for like six hours I'm
starting to get the shakes
I gotta have carbs I have to have
something to get my blood sugar up and
they threw a bologna sandwich at me
which you know came apart in the air and
was on the floor and one of the child
molesters picked it up and gave it to me
and then finally they put me in a single
cell again still cuffed I was able to
talk to one of my attorneys through like
a little confessional window but
little tiny bars in it and then they
took my tie and my shoestrings after the
fact after all this was over so I went
into court with no tie and no shoe
strings and then the last thing and let
this be a lesson to Julian too because
these guys they think they're so smart
and they're not I was arraigned I pled
not guilty and then they said you need
to go to the marshal's office they need
for you to sign some papers before you
leave well yeah what's it take five
seconds ten seconds maybe to assign some
papers but what they do is they make you
sit there for hours so that the media
that's waiting for you outside after
they they interview the prosecutors who
walk out of the courtroom they get tired
of waiting for you and they pack up and
they go home so when you finally leave
three hours later there's nobody out
there to get your side of the story
well my lawyers were smart enough to
know this so they said to me look
they're gonna make you sit here for the
rest of the afternoon let's go outside
now there's nothing to keep you in here
we'll go outside now we're gonna tell
every reporter in Washington with our
side of the story is and then we'll come
back and sign the papers well the
marshals saw us leaving we had only been
in that office for five minutes the
marshal saw sleeping and said hey you
can't leave and one of my attorneys
turned around and said you show me the
statute that says we can't leave go
ahead and look it up because we're gonna
be back in a half an hour so we left I
gave an interview to you know everybody
in Washington was out there waiting and
then I went back in they made me sit for
another hour and then I signed my
documents and left
I fear that Julian will not have the
luxury of leaving they'll probably lock
him up and keep him locked up and you
know I hope Julian is watching this or I
guess he can't because he doesn't have
internet access but I hope he hears
about it because I'm gonna repeat I'm
gonna repeat advice that I've tried to
convey to him in other venues if there's
anything that you can do to stay out of
the Eastern District of Virginia
do it because you will not get a fair
trial here the deck is stacked I was I
was so I was so panicked about being
wronged in the Eastern District that I
hired a jury consultant and mystery
consultant happened to be the uncle of
my best friend's wife and so his $10,000
a day fee cut he cut it to zero he did
it out of the goodness of his heart
this guy was OJ Simpson's jury a jury
consultant he was William Kennedy Smith
story consult me was George Zimmerman's
jury consultant so this is the real deal
so he came up to Washington he lives in
Dallas and we got him a security
clearance so he could read the
background of my case and then we all
got together now I was not allowed to
see my attorneys anywhere except in the
Justice Department's classified
conference room this is this is what
what Josh Schulte is going through and
this is how it's going to be for for
Julian as well you cannot speak to your
attorneys in their office because the
government's gonna argue that everything
that you have to say is classified and
so you have to talk to them in the
Justice Department's conference room
which of course is bugged of course they
have access to the computer that you're
working on of course they know what your
strategy is so you can't win in that
respect so so anyway these traditions of
Virginia I forget exactly
don't forget what I'm saying Joe I keep
going off on these tangents and now I
forget that's fine no no tell me what
was my point well they were saying that
you would hope they're drilling asunder
then they kind of stay out of it yes so
so oh the jury consultant so yeah comes
up and he reviews the case we have
15,000 pages of classified documents and
finally he says to me listen if we were
in any other district in America we'd
win this thing he said
haven't done anything wrong you haven't
broken the law but the Eastern District
of Virginia they don't call it the
espionage court for nothing no national
security defendant has ever won a case
ever in the Eastern District of Virginia
I said so what are you telling me to do
he said I'm telling you to take the deal
and so I I had to take the deal now the
only reason that I was as lucky as I was
is because my lawyers were geniuses the
the Washington Post called my attorneys
legal Titans they said that they were
the best white-collar criminal defense
attorneys in Washington that says a lot
and so they negotiated something for me
called an 11 C 1 C plea this is another
thing that I want to convey to Julianne
an 11 C 1 C plea is an agreement between
the prosecution and the defense that's
written in stone it cannot be changed
it could be rejected but it cannot be
changed and so rather than face 45 years
or realistically as my attorney said 18
years my writer has negotiated two and a
half years of which I would do 23 months
that was an 11 C 1 C and it went to the
judge as a take-it-or-leave-it
proposition so when she received it she
read it right there up at the bench and
she looked at me she told me to stand
and she said I have been a judge since
1986 this is the first 11 C 1 C plea I
have ever had she said I don't like it I
don't like it one bit and if it were up
to me I would give you the maximum and I
thought to myself what it actually is up
to you because if you weren't all talk
you could reject it and I could go to
trial and I could talk about the hideous
[__] that I saw at the CIA in the 15
years that I was there the last 7 being
in counterterrorism operations we and
you could imagine how filthy those are
so I just stood there and I thought to
myself so if you don't like it then
reject it and she says but my hands are
tied and I'm four
to accept it and she accepted it so
instead of the government asking for 45
years and me doing 18 years and probably
dying it in prison I ended up getting 2
and a half I did 23 months and I came
home
if Julian has any opportunity whatsoever
to negotiate an 11 C 1 C plea he's got
to do it it'll be the only thing that
saves him you don't think that's
realistic that he'll be able to do that
do you well you know I think it is
realistic because I think there's one
thing that Julian has on his side that
the government can't do a doggone thing
about and that's the notion of jury
nullification you know there are enough
right-thinking people out there
especially in a well-educated well
informed area like the Washington area
where they're gonna be people called for
jury selection who are gonna say this is
nonsense this guy did a public service
this guy exposed war crimes and crimes
against humanity just because the
government doesn't like him doesn't mean
he belongs in prison so I think the
government ought to be worried about
prospective jurors thinking wait a
minute this Assange guy is a hero he's
not a criminal and no matter what the
government has to say we're not gonna
vote to convict I think that's a real
possibility if though if they say that
during jury selection they won't get
selected there may be themselves to the
truck that's right during notification
is of course when when the government
can prove that the suspect broke the law
but the jury decides the law is unjust
it's the closest we have to a public
defense a public interest defense that
doesn't exist in the US but does in the
UK where you could say yes he leaked the
classified information and that's
technically against the law but it was
in the public interest can't mount that
defense in the US but that's the only
thing we might be able to rely on is
jury nullification I just wanted to say
John when you were talking about how you
were treated that day it did the irony
of it to these guys treating it like it
didn't dawn on them that you were there
because you had exposed torture and
that's how they were treating you so
it's really extraordinary one point I
was sitting in his chair before they put
me in the in the cage I was sitting in
this
chair and one of the mercial said how do
you spell your last name and just
instinctively I stood up to answer him
and he shouts at me [__] if you
stand up one more time I'm gonna break
your legs
and I said my god man does this make you
feel manly talking to people like what's
the matter with you Terry I sat back
down it's like okay so this is how it's
gonna be